Good morning, my name is Dan Margulis, I'm filling in for Rabbi
Linzer. Today is August 1st, it is the 26th of תמוז. Tammuz.
ראש חודש Rosh Chodesh is on Friday, and we are on בבא
קמא ס"ב Bava Kama Samech-Beis 62, around 10 lines down where it
says אמר רבא. Amar Rava. These cases start to get into some
of the little bits and pieces that were brought up by the
משנה. Mishnah. The משנה Mishnah mentioned a מחלוקת machlokes between רבי יהודה
Rabbi Yehuda and חכמים Chachamim about טמון, tamun, that is things that
are concealed, hidden inside of a haystack, and the haystack was burned
up. So obviously the person who lit the fire is liable for
the damage to the haystack, the question is whether or not items
which were hidden inside,
which presumably the owner of the fire was not aware of or
should not have needed to be aware of, so the liability there,
and then in which cases would you be liable for those kinds
of things as well. So it extends to a broader discussion of
liability based on how much שמירה, shemirah, how much guardianship did the
person accept upon themselves or not. So that's רבא's Rava case. So
it says אמר רבא, Amar Rava, רבא Rava said: הנותן דינר זהב
לאשה, ha-noten dinar zahav l'ishah, a person gave a golden coin to
a woman. Obviously the fact that it's a woman is not relevant
to the case, it's just happens to be that that was the
case that רבא Rava was dealing with. So you gave a golden
coin to a woman, ואמר לה היזהרי בו של כסף הוא, ve-amar
lah hizari bo shel kesef hu, and he said to her: be
careful with it, it's made of silver.
In fact, he was lying to her or misleading her. היזקתה משלמת
דינר זהב. hizaktah meshalemes dinar zahav.
If she damaged it directly, that is she threw it into a
fire, she hit it with a hammer, something like that, then she
should pay back the value of a gold דינר, dinar, which we
know is usually 25 times the value of a silver דינר dinar
in the גמרא. Gemara. Obviously the exchange rates between silver and gold
have changed somewhat since the time of the גמרא, Gemara, whether that's
a fixed rate or whether that's variable is an interesting question. So
משום דאמר לה, mishum d'amar lah, why, מאי הוה ליה גבה דאזקתיה,
mai havat lei gabah d'azaktai, why did you have to go and
destroy it? Meaning the fact that she went and damaged it, so
she should accept upon herself full liability for whatever it was even
if she wasn't aware that it was made of gold. Okay.
פשעה בו, pash'ah bo, but what if while she was watching it,
she did something negligent? We know that שומרים, shomrim, guardians over different
kinds of property, are liable if they do something negligent that causes
damage to the object. משלמת של כסף, meshalemes shel kesef, she only
pays back a silver דינר. dinar. דאמרה ליה, d'amrah lei, she can
say back to him: נטירותא דכספא קבילי עלי נטירותא דדהבא לא קבילי
עלי. netirusa d'chaspa kabili alai netirusa d'dahava lo kabili alai.
I only accepted upon myself the level of שמירה shemirah to guard
over something made of silver. That is, she only thought that it
was made of silver, and so that whole time she only accepted
upon herself that level of liability as a שומר, shomer, as a
שומרת. shomeres. So in that case, she would only pay back a
silver דינר dinar and not a gold דינר. dinar. Okay. So that's
רבא's Rava statement. Let's just turn to the מרדכי Mordechai quickly. The
מרדכי Mordechai uses this in a very interesting case. The מרדכי Mordechai
has a case: מעשה ששאל ראובן משמעון סייף שהיה לו במשכון. ma'aseh
she-sha'al Reuven mi-Shimon sayif she-hayah lo b'mashkon.
So ראובן Reuven borrowed a sword that שמעון Shimon had as a
משכון, mashkon, as a collateral on a loan that he had given
to a non-Jewish person. So a non-Jewish person borrowed money from שמעון,
Shimon, שמעון Shimon has the sword as collateral, and then ראובן Reuven
borrowed the sword.
Okay. ואבדו, ve-avdo, he lost it while he borrowed it. והיה שואל
לו שמעון דבר גדול כמו ששאל ממנו העובד כוכבים. ve-hayah sho'el lo
Shimon davar gadol k'mo she-sha'al mimenu ha-oved kochavim.
And then the non-Jew comes back and says this was actually a
very valuable antique sword that was worth a lot, a lot, a
lot of money and you didn't even know about it. And therefore
now שמעון Shimon is trying to claim that from ראובן. Reuven. And
the way the מרדכי Mordechai rules is he says no, the שומר
shomer only accepted upon himself, the שואל, sho'el, the borrower, only thought
that it was a regular sword, so he only accepted upon himself
the level of שמירה shemirah for the value of what he thought
a regular sword was worth and not a fancy, fancy heirloom. But
at the end he says צריך עיון. tzarich iyun. The מרדכי Mordechai
says really I'm not sure. Maybe it's not totally analogous to the
case in the גמרא. Gemara. And ים של שלמה, Yam Shel Shlomo,
the מהרש"ל, Maharshal, explains the difference, which is that in a case
here in the גמרא, Gemara, the גמרא's Gemara case is sort of
you had a reasonable expectation, sorry, it would be unreasonable to expect
anything more. Why? Because the person giving her the coin, the man
giving her the coin, said it is made of silver, so he
told her how much שמירה shemirah she should accept, or he was
actually trying to mislead her. But in this case, where ראובן Reuven
borrowed the sword from שמעון, Shimon, there was no deception and he
just said, okay, here's the sword, sort of take it at face
value. It could be worth however much, you don't know, but there
was no explicit mention. So that becomes a מחלוקת machlokes between the
מרדכי Mordechai and the ים של שלמה Yam Shel Shlomo about a
parallel case, interestingly just thinking about also it underlines the facts, the
historical reality, which is that Jews were very often in possession of
collateral on loans. From non-Jews because they were very often involved in
lending money. So that kind of mercantile trade economy influenced some of
the cases that came to the came to the rabbis at the
time. Okay. So we are on ס"ב ע"א Samech Bet Amud Aleph
and we'll continue. So אמר ליה רבי מרדכי לרב אשי. Amar lei
Rabbi Mordechai leRav Ashi. So רב מרדכי Rav Mordechai said to רב
אשי, Rav Ashi, so אתון בדרבא מתינו לה, אנן ממתניתין פשיטא לן.
Atun bi-de-Rava matinitu lah, anan mi-matnitin peshita lan.
So what, you're going to tell me that's a case from רבא?
Rava? What do you mean? Why do you need to quote it
from רבא? Rava? That's what this exact ברייתא braita says. So what
does the ברייתא braita say? So because he's obviously saying I can
learn the exact same הלכה halacha from the ברייתא. braita. So חטין
וחיפן בשעורין. Chittin ve-chipan bi-se'orin. If a person got permission to bring
a load of wheat into the חצר chatzer and leave it there
in a big pile and in the end he first dumped the
wheat and then he put barley on top. Barley we know is
worth less money.
Or שעורין וחיפן בחטין, se'orin ve-chipan be-chittin, or he first put barley
and then covered it up with wheat. So in one way or
another what is the main part of the haystack is actually covered
up with something else. Either if it looks like it's worth more
or it looks like it's worth less.
Okay. So אינו משלם אלא דמי שעורין בלבד. Eino meshalem ela dmei
se'orin bilvad. If it becomes damaged he only pays for שעורין, se'orin,
he only pays for barley one way or another. Either because in
the end the thing that got burned up was barley, the fact
that it had wheat on the outside was just a deception, or
the thing that got burned up was wheat but then that's טמון,
tamun, it was hidden inside. So either way the most he'll be
able to claim is the worth of the barley. So אלמא אמר
ליה נטירותא דשעורי קבילי עלי. Alma amar lei netiruta de-se'orei kabeili alai.
So in that case because the person who was watching it can
always claim, I only accepted upon myself to guard over a barley
which is worth less and not the wheat that's worth more. So
too the woman can say הכא נמי אמרה ליה נטירותא דדהבא לא
קבילי עלי. hacha nami amrah lei netiruta de-dahava lo kabeili alai. She
can always claim I never accepted to be a guardian over gold.
Okay. אמר רב. Amar Rav. So now a new case. רב Rav
said שמיע לי מילתא דרבי יהודה ולא ידענא מאי היא. Shame'at milta
de-Rabbi Yehuda ve-lo yadana mai hi. I remember we learned a הלכה
halacha about something about רבי יהודה's Rabbi Yehuda's שיטה shita and I
don't remember what it was. So אמר שמואל דלא ידע אבא מאי
שמיע ליה לרבי יהודה. Amar Shmuel de-lo yada Abba mai shame'a lei
le-Rabbi Yehuda. So meaning שמואל Shmuel who was רב's Rav's colleague speaks
to him very respectfully, he speaks to him in the third person,
he calls him אבא. Abba. Oh, door's blocked. Someone opened the door.
אבא ולא ידע אבא מאי שמיע ליה. Abba ve-lo yada Abba mai
shame'a lei. And does אבא Abba does father not know, meaning אבא,
Abba, רב Rav is also called אבא? Abba? So
does רב Rav not know what that הלכה halacha was from רבי
יהודה? Rabbi Yehuda? דרבי יהודה מחייב על נזקי טמון באש. De-Rabbi Yehuda
mechayev al nizkei tamun be-esh. So the fact is we know that
רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda says you're חייב chayav for טמון. tamun. That
is if something was concealed inside the fire inside the haystack and
the haystack burned down that you're still liable for whatever was hidden
inside. So the other הלכה halacha connected to רבי יהודה's Rabbi Yehuda's
שיטה shita that רב Rav had learned which he had forgotten: עשו
תקנת נגזל באשו. Asu takanat nigzal be-isho.
So they also made the תקנת נגזל, takanat nigzal, that is some
sort of תקנה, takana, דרבנן de-rabbanan תקנה takana to help a person
who was stolen from. So what does this mean? This is referring
to מסכת שבועות. Masechet Shavuot. In מסכת שבועות Masechet Shavuot we see
not only the שבועות דאורייתא, Shavuot De-Oraita, that is major categories of
oaths that you take in court at a biblical level. And the
biblical oaths are almost always נשבע ונפטר. nishba ve-niftar. You take a
שבועה shavuah to get out of an obligation. Someone comes to you
in a court case to make you liable and you can exempt
yourself by taking an oath. But the rabbis instituted many types of
oaths that are the reverse, that are in cases where it's uncertain
who should win the court case or if the court case has
already been determined but it's unsure how much should be paid out.
Then the claimant takes an oath in order to collect, נשבע
ונוטל. nishba ve-notel. And those are the rabbinic oaths. So this is
one of those cases, that is suppose the person got stolen from.
Someone stole my wallet and then I finally catch a thief but
he's passed it on to somebody else and he says, yeah but
there were only two dollars in your wallet. And I said what
do you mean, there were 200 dollars in my wallet. Okay. So
how much should the thief have to pay?
So in that case the person whose wallet it was, the נגזל,
nigzal, the person who was stolen from, takes an oath to swear
that it was 200 and then the thief has to pay 200.
So that's a נשבע ונוטל. nishba ve-notel. That's a rabbinic oath that
was instituted by the rabbis because otherwise a person who was stolen
from even if the thief admits to it is going to get
cheated out of his money. So that was called תקנת נגזל. takanat
nigzal. So according to within רבי יהודה's Rabbi Yehuda's שיטה, shita, רב
Rav had learned that even though since רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda says
you're חייב chayav for טמון באש, tamun be-esh, that is something concealed
within the haystack that got burned up you're also liable for it
and you have to pay back, so then you have to make
תקנת נגזל takanat nigzal because the person who owned that property is
going to claim, "Well, yeah, it was all sorts of expensive things,"
and the person whose fire it was can say, "What do you
mean? It was טמון. tamun. Nobody knows what it was." So there's
no way to know how much he should be liable for. So
that's why the person who was damaged should take this שבועה shvuah
in order to clarify how much money was at stake in this
case. Okay. So therefore, it makes perfect sense within רב יהודה'ס Reb
Yehuda's שיטה shita to say that they made תקנת נגזל takanas nigzal
as well. בעי אמימר. Ba'ei Amimar. So אמימר Amimar asked. Now אמימר
Amimar is much later than רב Rav and שמואל. Shmuel. אמימר Amimar
asked a question: עשו תקנת נגזל במוסר או לא? asu takanas nigzal
bemoser o lo? So do we make תקנת נגזל takanas nigzal by
a מוסר? moser? A מוסר moser is a person who had turned
over someone else's money to the non-Jewish authorities. We know obviously there's
a lot been discussed nowadays about how much these הלכות halachos apply
to modern governments that have modern criminal justice systems and all sorts
of things. I forget now which פוסק posek it was. I think
it may have been the ציץ אליעזר Tzitz Eliezer who says the
extent to which we apply the הלכות halachos of מוסר moser is
inversely proportional to how much we say דינא דמלכותא דינא. dina demalchusa
dina. That is, if we're comfortable with the extent to which the
civil authorities exert their power over civil law, criminal law in the
countries we live in, then we should be less concerned or less
fearful that if a Jewish person turns another Jewish person over to
those authorities that they're going to do anything unscrupulous or illegal. That
is, we trust them. So if we trust the civil authorities, then
we don't have to worry about מוסר moser so much. The problem
is much more in a case where there's a discriminatory government or
there's an anti-semitic government which is going to manipulate the law against
a Jew. And therefore, if one Jewish person turns another Jewish person
over to a court system which is going to treat them unfairly,
well then obviously what you've done is you've set up a case
where that person's money is going to be taken away. Or in
this case, perhaps they're going to be overcharged on taxes, things like
that. So מוסר ממונו של חבירו, moser mamono shel chaveiro, you're giving
over someone else's money to the authorities. So in that case, it's
a kind of גזילה, gzeila, because what did you do? You said,
"Oh, so and so owes this much money in back taxes," and
you told the government. Well, maybe he doesn't really owe that much
money, but what you're doing is you're getting the government to take
his money away. So that's a kind of גזילה, gzeila, that's a
kind of theft. And the problem is, you know, once they take
the money away, so then the person is going to need to
claim, "Well, how much money did I lose because of this?" He's
going to need תקנת נגזל takanas nigzal as well. So that's אמימר'ס
Amimar's question. But he doesn't know whether חז"ל Chazal actually enacted that
שבועה shvuah in that case or not. In other words,
perhaps you can say: is it really like a kind of גזל
gezel or not? So we're going to see. אליבא דמאן דאמר לא
דיינינן דינא דגרמי לא תיבעי לך, aliba deman de'amar lo dayninan dina
degarmi lo tiba'i lach, דמסירות נמי לא דיינינן. demasiros nami lo dayninan.
So he says: according to the one who says we don't treat
cases of גרמי garmi as liable, well then it's obvious because this
is at best a kind of גרמי garmi because what did you
do? You told someone else to take this person's money away. You
didn't have any direct action involved. And so therefore the worst you
can say is that it was גרמי. garmi. And therefore if we
don't treat גרמי garmi as a real נזק, nezek, then there's nothing
you can say here. Okay. אלא כי תיבעי לך אליבא דמאן דאמר
דיינינן דינא דגרמי. ela ki tiba'i lach aliba deman de'amar dayninan dina
degarmi. But if we hold like the opinion that says that we
do consider דיני דגרמי—and dinei degarmi look in רש"י, Rashi, רש"י Rashi
says, "Wait, hold your horses, we're getting there in קט"ז עמוד ב',
kuf tes vav amud beis, we'll be there in a few months."
Okay. So according to אמימר, Amimar, עשו תקנת נגזל במוסר? asu takanas
nigzal bemoser? So they did apply תקנת נגזל takanas nigzal to the
case of מוסר? moser? דמשתבע ושקיל או לא? demishtaba veshakil o lo?
And that's a question: should you take this oath and take the
money or not? He says תיקו. teiku. So אמימר'ס Amimar's question is
left unanswered. Okay. So number one, the מחלוקת machlokes about דיני דגרמי
dinei degarmi here seems interesting. That is, we have one opinion that
says we don't consider דיני דגרמי. dinei degarmi. That is, it's basically
the same as גרמא, grama, and we say גרמא בנזיקין פטור. grama
benizikin patur.
The opinion that says דיני דגרמי dinei degarmi is חייב, chayav, still
we have a difference between the case of גרמי garmi and a
regular נזק nezek seemingly, because there's still a מחלוקת machlokes about whether
or not you would say תקנת נגזל takanas nigzal or not. So
it becomes a question. תוספות רבינו פרץ Tosafos Rabbeinu Peretz here based
on the תוספות Tosafos on נ"ד nun daled says, well this סוגיא
sugya is proof that even if you hold by גרמי, garmi, it's
not a real, it's not מדאורייתא. mide'oraisa. It can't be the same
as regular נזק nezek because otherwise why would there even be a
question? Once you say דיני דגרמי, dinei degarmi, it will be equivalent
to regular נזק. nezek. And the רמב"ן Ramban is of the opinion:
no, דיני דגרמי dinei degarmi is דאורייתא. de'oraisa. It's equivalent to regular
נזק, nezek, and so the רמב"ן Ramban has to say nonetheless there
must be a difference here between the kind of damage caused by
גרמי garmi and direct damage even though they both operate at the
דאורייתא de'oraisa level. So there's that distinction there between them even though
they're somewhat equivalent. Okay.
So it's left as a תיקו. teiku. It's unresolved. The problem with
תיקו teiku of course, we don't know how to פסקן pasken whether
or not we would say תקנת נגזל takanas nigzal in this case,
is then what do you do if this case comes up? Who
wins? Because what happens? We have now a case someone says, "Yeah,
it was מוסר moser him to the government but they only charged
him five dollars," and this guy says, "No, So he was מוסר
moser him to the government and they charged me five hundred dollars.
So who pays how much? So if you look in the תוספות
Tosfos עשו תקנת נגזל במוסר או לא, Asu Takanas Nigzal BiMoser o
lo, so תוספות Tosfos first quotes from the רי"ף Rif כגון שיש
עדים שמסרו ואיבד בממונו ואין יודעין כמה. kegon sheyesh edim shemasro ve'ibed
bemamono ve'ein yode'in kama. So תיקו teiku וכל תיקו דממונא לקולא. vechol
teiku demamona lekula. So we have to פסקן pasken תיקו teiku לקולא
lekula in ממונות mammonous cases and לקולא lekula means you can only
make him pay the five dollars because anything more than that you
need proof to be able to make someone pay. Okay, בהאי גוונא,
behaigone, interestingly enough, כתוב שישלם מחצה. kasuv sheyeshallem chatzi. You pay half.
That is, take the difference between five and five hundred is 495,
495 and half is 242, 200 what? 247.5,
right. Okay, so that's because it's a ממון המוטל בספק חולקין, mammon
hamutul besafek cholkin, like סומכוס's Sumchos opinion, we should split the difference,
and the ר"י Ri doesn't like either of those, ואיני נראה לרי
דחייב כלל משום תיקו. ve'ein nireh lari dechayav klal mishum teiku. We
shouldn't make you חייב chayav at all because תיקו teiku means fundamentally
we can't do anything, not just you should pay the מיקל meikel
position, but actually that the תיקו teiku means in this case that
we can't resolve the case at all. Okay, and the רבינו תם
Rabbeinu Tam has an answer. So anyway, it's just interesting to see
that the way we resolve a תיקו teiku in this case becomes
a bit tricky because there's a חומרא chumra and there's a קולא
kula and it's a חומרא chumra for one and a קולא kula
for another, it becomes complicated. Okay. So we continue the גמרא Gemara
on the fifth wide line on ס"ב עמוד א'. samech-bet amud aleph.
ההוא גברא דבטש בכספתא דחבריה. Hahu gavra debata beshafsa dechavra. A person
kicked his friend's money box. Okay. Now obviously kicking it isn't enough,
it has to be you kicked it into some place where it
disappeared or it got totally lost.
Okay, שדייה בנהרא, shadye binahara, and it went into the river. So
אתא מרי, ata marei, the owner of the money box came ואמר
הכי והכי הוה לי בגוויה, ve'amar hachi vehachi hava li begavei, and
he says, well this is how much money was in the money
box. Well that makes sense, that's kind of like תקנת נגזל. takanas
nigzal. He's making a claim of how much money he was lost,
and hopefully it seems like we should be able to get him
back his money. So יתיב רב אשי, yativ Rav Ashi, Rav Ashi
was sitting וקא מעיין בה כהאי גוונא, veka mayein bei kehai gavna,
כהאי גוונא מאי. kehai gavna mai.
So Rav Ashi says was sitting down and thinking carefully about this
case, he says I don't know what to do exactly. Okay. אמר
ליה רבינא לרב אחא בריה דרבא, amar lei Ravina leRav Acha brei
deRava, and Ravina said to רב אחא בריה דרבא Rav Acha brei
deRava ואמרי לה, ve'amrei lah, רב אחא בריה דרבא לרב אשי, Rav
Acha brei deRava leRav Ashi, perhaps רב אחא בריה דרבא Rav Acha
brei deRava said directly to רב אשי Rav Ashi to advise him
on this case what should be the דין, din, והיינו מתניתין, vehai
matnitin, isn't this the case in the Mishnah? דתנן detnan ומודים חכמים
לרבי יהודה במדליק את הבירה שמשלם כל שבתוכה. umodim chachamim leRabbi Yehuda
bemadliket habira shemeshallem kol shebechocho. That the חכמים chachamim agree to רבי
יהודה Rabbi Yehuda that if a person lit a fire and it
burned up the house that you have to pay back whatever was
in the house. Whatever is in a house doesn't count as טמון
tamun the same way that it would count in a haystack, and
so even the חכמים chachamim agree that whatever is in the house
you have to pay back. But what do חכמים chachamim say you
have to pay back? משלם כל מה שבתוכה שכן דרך בני אדם
להניח בבתים. meshallem kol mah shebetocho sheken derech benei adam lehaniach bevattim.
What to pay back whatever it is that people normally keep in
their houses, that is you can't claim above and beyond that. You
can't say, oh, I had some antique thing and whatever was worth
a lot of money because then you have no proof and then
they'll say well that's just like טמון, tamun, that is it's not
expected. But just like חכמים chachamim would even admit something that might
be טמון tamun
that was to be expected, well then the liability makes sense because
the liability, the exemption by טמון tamun is that you wouldn't have
expected it to be there. But if it's something that you would
have expected to be there, then it makes perfect sense that you
should have to pay. Okay, so too in this case. אמר ליה,
amar lei, אי דקא טעין זוזי הכא נמי. ee deka ta'ein zuzei
hacha nami. So one case would be if you're claiming זוזי zuzei
money for what's in the box, right?
הכא במאי עסקינן? hacha bemai askinan? דקא טעין מרגניתא. deka ta'ein marganita.
He claimed that it was full of pearls, it was full of
jewels. And so obviously the claim he's making is beyond what you
would have expected in this case. He had a cash box, fine
if it would have been full of money it would have been
one thing. That would have been a normal claim. But here he's
saying I had something much more valuable hidden inside the box, and
therefore that's the question why רב אשי Rav Ashi even had a
question. And that's why רב אחא בריה דרבא's Rav Acha brei deRava
answer, it said, oh, isn't it a מתניתין? matnitin? Well, רב אשי
Rav Ashi has to actually sit and think about it because it
wasn't just that Mishnah. The claim was actually he was making a
higher claim and nonetheless maybe he would have even considered that, so
we'll have to see. Okay.
So מאי? mai? אי מנח איניש מרגניתא בכספתא או לא? ee mancha
inish marganita bekaspasa o lo? Do people normally put מרגניתא marganita pearls
in their cash boxes or לא? lo? Maybe they don't? תיקו. teiku.
And it's again left unresolved. So that is רב אשי Rav Ashi
still was unsure how to פסקן pasken in this case. Do we
say, well a cash box is just where you put valuable things
and even putting pearls there would be somewhat expected and that's why
it would be reasonable to allow him to take תקנת נגזל takanas
nigzal perhaps or even just to pay back even without having to
take a שבועה shvua in this case because it's exactly like the
Mishnah? Or maybe there's a difference, it's not expected and therefore there
would be a difference. Yeah. If somebody could bring a witness to
say I saw this valuable painting in the house or the jewel
in the box, then they would, so perhaps it becomes interesting question
if you could, a week ago I had... had the pearls in
the box but then I took the pearls out put money in
and then he kicked the box so you know how much time
in between
would make the witness relevant presumably would have to be relatively soon
before the damage occurred. And I mean I imagine for both a
house and this but maybe you'd have to factor in for socioeconomics
although like a house in one neighborhood versus a house in another
and what's normally inside. Ah so we're going to see. Okay that's
going to come up in the question of of who who is
involved may may impact this as well. Just one other point which
is that in a totally different context in מסכת כלים Masechet Kelim
talking about different types of containers the משניות mishnayot distinguish between a
צרור המרגלית tsror hamargalit a piece of leather that's been folded up
to hold pearls and a צרור מעות tsror maot that you made
the same kind of pouch to put coins in because the one
that you put the pearls usually you're not opening it and closing
it so it retains its status as a כלי kli more permanently
the one that you use for your wallet well you open it
up take the money out put the money in close it back
up again every day it could be multiple times a day so
it's much less a permanent כלי kli but the leather piece that
you're using to hold pearls you close it up and you leave
it for a year at a time two years you never check
on your pearls you put them in the bank as it were.
So that kind of difference of how people are accessing and how
people are using money versus pearls comes up in a number of
other contexts.
Okay. So אמר ליה רב יימר לרב אשי amar lei Rav Yeimar
le-Rav Ashi so Rav Yeimar says to Rav Ashi טען כסא דכספא
בבירא מאי taen kasa de-khaspa be-bira mai what if a person claimed
there was a silver goblet in my house when the house burned
down so what should be the case? אמר ליה amar lei חזינא
אי איניש אמיד הוא דאית ליה כסא דכספא khazina i inish amid
hu de-it lei kasa de-khaspa so we should see well is he
a fancy important rich person that he has a silver goblet in
his house in order that that would be a reasonable claim? אי
נמי i nami איניש מהימנא הוא דמפקידי אינשי גביה inish mehemnah hu
de-mapkidei inishei gabei or perhaps he's a reliable person who even though
if he's not rich enough to own a silver cup but people
would have asked him to be their שומר shomer that is he's
a reliable person who he could have been the שומר shomer for
someone else? Okay so if that's the case משתבע ושקיל mishtaba ve-shakil
then he can take the שבועה shvua and collect that is take
as if this same תקנת נגזל takanas nigzal kind of נשבע ונוטל
nishba ve-notel שבועה shvua in order to actually collect the full value.
Okay ואי לאו ve-ee lav so אי לאו לאו כל מיניה ee
lav lav kol minei so and if not then there's no reason
for us to assume that he that he would have such a
valuable object that he would be it would make any sense for
him to make such a claim. Interestingly enough you could say so
who cares? He should still be allowed the opportunity to take the
שבועה shvua interestingly enough we still need grounds we still need a
certain amount of grounds to authorize him to take a שבועה shvua
in that case. So Jenna that actually answered your question directly which
is that the economic status or perhaps the person's reliability and trustworthiness
come into play in terms of evaluating whether this claim is a
reasonable claim to say yeah there was this fancy object in my
house or not and it goes David your question as well. Okay.
So אמר רב אבא בריה דרב אביא לרב אשי amar Rav Abba
brei de-Rav Avia le-Rav Ashi מה בין גזלן לחמסן? ma bein gazlan
le-khamsan? Now a totally different question but interesting a lot of מפרשים
mefarshim try to say like why is this here? It seems totally
off topic but not for now תוספות Tosafot seems to discuss it
quite a bit.
Okay. What is the difference between a גזלן gazlan an armed robber
or a robber at least and a חמסן khamsan someone who we're
going to see the חמסן khamsan is someone who pressures someone into
stealing into selling something that they really didn't want to sell. That's
what it seems like. So what's the difference between גזלן וחמסן? gazlan
ve-khamsan? אמר ליה amar lei חמסן יהיב דמי khamsan yahiv damei a
חמסן khamsan actually pays the money וגזלן לא יהיב דמי ve-gazlan lo
yahiv damei a גזלן gazlan doesn't pay for it. A גזלן gazlan
took it from you and the חמסן khamsan is the one who
forced you to sell it. Now interestingly enough they're basically being equated
in terms of what עבירה avera is at play here. Perhaps in
the end what happened? This person came to you and attacked you
and made you give made them give you something.
Perhaps the difference really I mean the major difference is whether or
not they paid for it that is is it theft or not?
חמסן khamsan obviously has different הלכות halakhot and what עבירה avera have
you violated if you're a חמסן khamsan really? That's the other question.
So it seems like and again the ראשונים rishonim deal with this
at length the question is לא תחמוד. lo takhmod. לא תחמוד lo
takhmod seems to include this kind of עבירה avera of forcing someone
to sell something that they didn't want
and for people who who are not familiar with it perhaps good
to take take a look later the רמב"ם Rambam and the ראב"ד
Ra'avad have a I would say relatively classic מחלוקת machloket about לא
תחמוד. lo takhmod. The רמב"ם Rambam seems to say לא תחמוד lo
takhmod not coveting someone else's property that's a
לאו שאין בו מעשה lav she-ein bo ma'aseh it has no active
active action in in the violation therefore that's why you don't get
you don't get lashes for that because there's no action all it
was a mental or a psychological state of wanting something from someone
else even if it needs a certain kind of result it's not
just oh I want... Wanted someone something, but I actually had to
pressure them to do something. So the ראב''ד *Ra'avad* says, well what
do you mean? If the whole point is that you had to
pressure them to give it to you, you had to bug them
until they sold it to you, so what do you mean it's
a לאו שאין בו מעשה *lav she'ein bo ma'aseh*? Of course that's
the מעשה *ma'aseh*. That's the action. So the ראב''ד *Ra'avad* says no,
the difference is because it's דאיתא בתשלומין *de'ita betashlumin*, you can pay
it back. And that's why you don't get מכות *makos*. You don't
get מכות *makos* just like if you're a thief you don't get
מכות *makos* because you pay back the money.
And so obviously there's a big discussion about like what actually is
the violation of לא תחמוד *lo tachmod*, it's perhaps the most perplexing
of the ten commandments
because again there's a big מחלוקת *machlokes*, what does it mean? Is
it only psychological? Is it a sort of connected to the idea
of stealing?
And one other point is that the ספר החינוך *Sefer HaChinuch* in
talking about לא תתאוה *lo titaveh*, the מצוה mitzvah *mitzvah* as it
appears in דברים *Devarim*, the ספר החינוך *Sefer HaChinuch* says okay, so
he says לא תתאוה *lo titaveh* applies to non-Jews as well. And
what do you mean? We have only seven מצוות mitzvot בני נח
*mitzvot bnei noach*. Which of the seven מצוות בני נח *mitzvot bnei
noach* is לא תתאוה *lo titaveh*? He says it's actually part of
גניבה gneiva
וגזילה *gneivah vegezeilah* of theft. And the reason why is because actually
the seven מצוות בני נח *mitzvot bnei noach* are just major categories
and they have subcategories of מצוות *mitzvot* within them. Obviously עבודה זרה
*avodah zarah* contains many different prohibitions, גילוי עריות *giluy arayot* contains many
different prohibitions, but they're headings. The seven major categories each has sub-sub-מצוות
*mitzvot* as well. Okay. So that's the difference between חמסן *chamsan* and
גזלן *gazlan* is whether they pay or not. אמר ליה *amar lei*,
אי הכי דמי חמסן קרית ליה *i hachei damei chamsan kayeit lei*.
Is it really true that if a person gives the money they're
a חמסן *chamsan*? והאמר *veha'amar* רב הונא *Rav Huna*, but רב הונא
*Rav Huna* talked about exactly this kind of case. תליוה וזבין *talyuha
vezavin*, זביניה זבינא *zavinei zavina*. If a person threatened you and forced
you to sell something, you're at gunpoint and they say 'sell me
your car and here's $20,000, give me your car,' at gunpoint, זביניה
זבינא *zavinei zavina*, that's a good sale.
So what, that's not a חמסן *chamsan*? That's a sale. The fact
that you were under duress, okay fine, but nonetheless, meaning in the
end you still paid the money. So לא קשיא *lo kashya*, there's
no, here's the distinction. הא דאמר רוצה אני, הא דלא אמר רוצה
אני *ha de'amar rotzeh ani, ha de'lo amar rotzeh ani*. It's the
difference whether the person said 'I want to' or not. That is,
the person said 'okay fine I'll do it' and gets the $20,000,
gives away the car, is different than if he never said רוצה
אני *rotzeh ani*. If he never said רוצה אני *rotzeh ani*, that's
a חמסן *chamsan*. In that case, he's been forced to the point
of never being willing to go through with it or not.
Of course, this distinction about רוצה אני *rotzeh ani* and not, the
רמב''ם *Rambam* doesn't quote in משנה mishna תורה Torah *Mishneh Torah*. So
it's interesting to consider, well that seems to be the answer here
between what's the difference between a חמסן *chamsan* compared to רב הונא's
*Rav Huna's* case and then the רמב''ם *Rambam* leaves it out. More
to be said about that. Let's turn the page, the last משנה
mishna *mishnah* in פרק הכונס Perek Hakones. *perek hakoneis*.
The משנה Mishnah. *mishnah* says, גץ שיצא מתחת הפטיש *gaits sheyatza mitachat
hapatish*. If a spark flies out from underneath the hammer, that is
the hammer of a blacksmith of some kind, והזיק *vehizik*, and it
flew from the רשות היחיד reshut hayachid? *reshut hayachid* into רשות הרבים
reshut harabbim, *reshut harabim*, חייב chayav. *chayav* because that's how אש *esh*
works. אש *esh* spreads, so a גץ *gaits* is categorized as אש
*esh* in that sense. גמל gamal שהיה טעון פשתן ועובר ברשות הרבים
*gamal shehaya ta'un pishtan ve'over bereshut harabim*, a camel was loaded up,
very piled up, with flax. Flax being very flammable. And the camel
was walking through רשות הרבים reshut harabbim, *reshut harabim* in the street,
ונכנס פשתנו לתוך החנות *venichnas pishtano letoch hachanut* and the flax, because
it was so overladen, the flax pushed through the window into somebody's
store and lit on fire on the candle, הדליקה בנרו של חנוני
chanvani *hadalko benero shel chanvani*, and it lit on the lamp or
the candle of the shop owner, והדליק את הבירה *vehidlik et habirah*
and then the fire on top of the camel lit the whole
building on fire. בעל הגמל ba'al hagamal חייב *baal hagamal chayav*. The
owner of the camel is liable because the camel should not have
been carrying such a flammable object in such a way that it
would actually penetrate into someone else's property. That is, it's one thing
if the camel was just walking in the street normally, but if
the camel's flax was so big that it pushed into רשות reshut?
היחיד *reshut hayachid* into a place where the person didn't think they'd
have to be so careful about the lamp, then that's the camel
owner's fault. הניח חנוני נרו מבחוץ *hiniach chanvani nero mibachutz*, if the
shop owner put his lamp outside, that is in רשות הרבים reshut
harabbim *reshut harabim*, החנוני חייב *hachanvani chayav*. So he's חייב *chayav* because
the whole problem is that he put something dangerous, in this case
the fire, into the רשות הרבים reshut harabbim. *reshut harabim*. So obviously
anyone who's going to be damaged by that, even if it burns
down a whole building, he's liable because he put it in a
place where it wasn't secure and it wasn't safe. So interestingly enough,
we see multiple times in חז''ל Chazal *Chazal*, not just here but
also in other places, that the equivalent of bringing the fuel for
the fire and bringing the flame itself, that is, here what happened?
Either the בעל הגמל ba'al hagamal *baal hagamal* brought the fuel to
the lamp, well in that case he's liable because he brought the
fuel and fed the fire, or if the person brought the fire
into the place where the גמל gamal *gamal* was, then the person
who brought the fire is חייב *chayav*. So actually both cases we
see it's similar to הלכות שבת Hilchot Shabbat *hilchot Shabbat* it comes
up, there's a ברייתא *baraita* in ביצה *Beitzah*. So a number of
cases where you see the equivalence between bringing the fuel and bringing
the fire. Ah, and one of the only seven places in the
משנה Mishnah that talks about חנוכה, Chanukah, רבי יהודה אומר בנר חנוכה
פטור. Rabbi Yehuda omer b'ner Chanukah patur. If it was a חנוכה
Chanukah candle that you were setting out in רשות הרבים, reshut harabbim,
then even in that case the חנוני will be פטור patur because
there's a special license we're going to see to put your חנוכה
Chanukah candle into the public street. Yes. Is it just a question
of who brought what? It's also a question of intruding on רשות
הרבים, reshut harabbim, רשות היחיד? Correct, that is also true, which is
the בעל הגמל transporting something through רשות הרבים reshut harabbim is one
thing and putting your candle, you're not going to put your candle
into the street, you're going to put your candle on your on
your shop desk. Exactly, the בעל הגמל was overflowing into the רשות
הרבים. reshut harabbim. Exactly, that's the case, exactly. So now the question
is what if they both had רשות? Well, then it's going to
be whoever did something different, so in that case it's going to
be like right. Okay. אמר רבינא משמיה דרבא. Amar Ravina mishmei deRava.
So רבינא Ravina said in the name of רבא, Rava, שמע מינה
מדברי רבי יהודה נר חנוכה מצוה להניחה בתוך עשרה. shma mina midivrei
Rabbi Yehuda ner Chanukah mitzvah lehaniha betoch asarah. From רבי יהודה's Rabbi
Yehuda position, we can learn that it is a מצוה mitzvah, to
put the חנוכה Chanukah candle within ten טפחים tfachim of the ground.
Now, if you ask most people where they put their חנוכה Chanukah
candle, most people probably put it on a table or something. Our
tables are relatively close to ten טפחים, tfachim, but some people put
it on the windowsill, some people put it up higher, it becomes
a question. So we know that בדיעבד bedi'eved or in certain cases,
particularly for people who live in apartment buildings,
the laws are more flexible. For an apartment building, if you הדר
בעליה, hadar ba'aliya, you just put it in the window facing רשות
הרבים, reshut harabbim. that's the best you can do, so that's what
you do. But in the case where a person has a house
and they're putting it out by the street, it has to be
within ten טפחים tfachim of the ground. A lot has been written
about that from a Hasidic perspective in particular about the flame of
חנוכה Chanukah being close to the ground in where it's darkest, where
it's, you know, deep down. It's not something you bring very high
up to spread the light everywhere, it's something sort of smaller and
deeper.
Okay. So מצוה להניחה בתוך עשרה, mitzvah lehaniha betoch asarah, דאי סלקא
דעתך למעלה מעשרה. de'isalka da'atach lemala me'asarah. If you would have said
maybe you could put it above עשרה, asarah, אמאי, amai, אמר רבי
יהודה נר חנוכה פטור? amar Rabbi Yehuda ner Chanukah patur? So why
should you say that you're פטור patur if it caught the camel
on fire? לימא ליה הוה ליה לאנחותיה למעלה מגמל ורוכבו. leima leh
hava leh le'anhutei lemala migamal verochvo. Then the safe thing to do
if you're putting it out in the street would be to put
it somewhere up here so that it's above wherever there would be
any risk of lighting a גמל on fire. You put it up
here, you know, three אמות amot above the רשות הרבים, reshut harabbim
and that should solve the problem. Tangentially, we also remember from הלכות
halachos. שבת that only the lowest ten טפחים tfachim of רשות הרבים
reshut harabbim are halachically categorized as רשות הרבים. reshut harabim. We know
the הלכה halacha of throwing the figs against the wall, that if
the fig lands on the wall above ten טפחים, tfachim, it's actually
not considered to be carrying because even though it comes to rest,
it comes to rest in a place that's not רשות הרבים. It
comes to rest above ten טפחים, tfachim, it's called מקום פטור. makom
p'tor. It's a totally exempted domain. So too here, the חנוכה Chanukah
candle actually has to be in the רשות הרבים part of רשות
הרבים and not above that.
So if you could have put it in a safer place, then
you would be חייב. Comes רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda to say it
must be put in a place where it דווקא davka actually is
dangerous, that is, if there's a safe place up here and you
could put it there, no, no, you have to put it down
here even though it's unsafe.
Okay. אמר רבי יהודה נר חנוכה פטור, ולימא ליה הוה ליה לאנחותה
למעלה מגמל ורוכבו. Amar Rabbi Yehuda ner Chanukah patur, v'leima leh hava
leh le'anhutah lemala migamal verochvo. אלא לאו שמע מינה מצוה להניחה בתוך
עשרה. ela lav shma mina mitzvah lehaniha betoch asarah. Obviously you have
to put it within עשרה asarah of the ground. אמרי, Amri, לא
לעולם אימא לך אפילו למעלה מעשרה. lo le'olam eima lach afilu lemala
me'asarah. Maybe you could say even above עשרה. asarah. So מאי אמרת
דהוה ליה לאנחותיה למעלה מגמל ורוכבו? mai amrat di'hava leh le'anhutei lemala
migamal verochvo? So then,
but then if you're allowed to put it above עשרה, asarah, why
would you not say, so then he has an obligation to put
it someplace safe, that is above the level of a גמל and
its rider? כיון דבמצוה
קא עסיק כולי האי לא אטרוהו רבנן. Keivan d'be'mitzvah ka asik kulei
hai lo atruhu Rabbanan.
The רבנן Rabbanan did not make you put it in a place
that's more difficult. You know, you need to get a special thing
attached to your wall and all sorts of stuff to put it
up very high. So the רבנן Rabbanan said, no, no, you're doing
a מצוה, mitzvah. we're going to make it easy for you, put
it down low. That is, even according to the opinion that it
could be put above עשרה, asarah, still you'd be פטור patur if
it causes damage because you put it out in the street, you
put it out in the street and that's where you were supposed
to put it, whether or not it was above עשרה, asarah, below
עשרה. asarah. The point is we don't make you put it anywhere
safe because we want you to be able to do the מצוה.
mitzvah,
חנוכה Chanukah candles, interestingly enough, one of the מצוות for which the
רבנן Rabbanan encouraged people very strongly that they have to do this
מצוה, mitzvah even שואל על הפתחים, sho'el al haptachim, you have to
beg for money in order to be able to afford oil for
a חנוכה Chanukah lamp.
So here too, the רבנן Rabbanan wanted to enable people to do
this מצוה as best as possible, even if it meant in this
case putting something rather dangerous into the public street. Okay. אמר רב
כהנא דרש רב נתן בר מניומי משמיה דרבי תנחום. Amar Rav Kahana
darash Rav Natan bar Minyumi mishmei deRabbi Tanchum. נר חנוכה שהניחה למעלה
מעשרים אמה. Ner Chanukah shehinichah lemala me'esrim amah. If you put your
חנוכה Chanukah candle above twenty אמה, amah, very high, twenty אמה amah
is around what, 30 feet or so, פסולה, psulah, כסוכה וכמבוי. k'Sukkah
u'ch'Mavoi. It's like a סוכה Sukkah and like a מבוי. Mavoi. The
סוכה, Sukkah, of course, we know the first דף daf in סוכה,
Sukkah, the three-way מחלוקת אמוראים machloket Amoraim about why the סוכה Sukkah
cannot
be...
רבה's Rabba opinion, the opinion that's most often quoted, is because if
if you are sitting in a סוכה sukkah that is taller than
twenty אמות, amot, you won't recognize that you're sitting in a סוכה
sukkah at that point. You won't realize it. You won't be able
to see the roof. You won't be able to see the סכך
s'chach because it's too tall. And that's the opinion that actually fits
the best here, that is, if it's above twenty אמות, amot, you
won't see it normally, because it's so high. People walking in the
street, people don't look up thirty feet high above the street, and
therefore you won't be able to notice the roof. The other opinions,
רבי זירא Rabbi Zeira says because the reason is that a person
with the סוכה, sukkah, sorry I'm forgetting רבי זירא's Rabbi Zeira opinion,
רבא's Rava opinion is that
you make in order to build something that's twenty אמות amot tall,
you actually have to make it very durable, very permanent, and therefore
if you're building something very durable, that's called a דירת קבע, dirat
keva, not דירת עראי. dirat arai. That's not a temporary structure that
the סוכה sukkah is supposed to be. It's actually much more permanent.
The מבוי, mavoy, the מבוי mavoy is the cross-beam at the entrance
way to an alleyway. So the cross-beam at the entrance way of
the קורה, kora, sorry, the קורה kora is the cross-beam that you
put at the entrance way to the מבוי mavoy to the alleyway.
The first משנה Mishnah in עירובין Eruvin also has to be below
twenty אמות amot and for the same reason that above twenty אמות
amot a person won't recognize it. So when they come to the
end of the מבוי mavoy where the עירוב eruv ends, they won't
realize it and then they'll walk straight into רשות הרבים. Interestingly enough,
you know, our modern עירובין eruvin very often are not so visible
to the untrained eye. It actually seems to be for חז"ל was
a major concern was that people would reach the edge of where
the עירוב eruv was and would keep going. So perhaps we have
a similar question nowadays and how much the way they're constructed or
the way they're publicized perhaps fulfills that requirement as well. So we
say הדרן עלך הכונס, hadran alach Hakones, that's the end of פרק
הכונס. We'll continue with פרק מרובה Perek Meruba right now. פרק מרובה
Perek Meruba starts our discussion of גניבה gneiva, and גזילה, gzeila, theft.
We've already seen a couple of topics come up about this already
and it's going to be dealt with in much more depth.
The משנה Mishnah says, מרובה מידת תשלומי כפל ממידת תשלומי ארבעה וחמישה.
meruba midat tashlumei kefel mimidat tashlumei arba ve-chamisha. The תורה Torah provides
two different kinds of fines in a case of גניבה, in a
case of theft,
burglary, that is something done in secret. If you steal something as
a גנב, ganav, you have to pay it back and you have
to pay back כפל, kefel, that is a one hundred percent value
fine, that is כפל, kefel, double the value. That's how much you
have to pay back. And the תורה Torah provides a special הלכה
halacha that in a case of stealing a sheep or a cow,
then if you either slaughtered the animal or if you sold it
to someone else, then you have to pay back a fine four
or five times the value of the animal, that is, four times
for sheep and five times for the cow, and that's actually a
very steep fine. So we're going to see all that discussed here,
but the point is, מרובה מידת תשלומי כפל ממידת תשלומי ארבעה וחמישה.
meruba midat tashlumei kefel mimidat tashlumei arba ve-chamisha. There are more cases
perhaps, or there is more about the cases of כפל, kefel, is
more general or more broadly applicable than ארבעה וחמישה, arba ve-chamisha, ד"ה.
daled hey. שמידת תשלומי כפל נוהגת בין בדבר שיש בו רוח חיים
ובין בדבר שאין בו רוח חיים. she-midat tashlumei kefel noheget bein bedavar
sheyesh bo ruchach hayyim uvein bedavar she-ein bo ruchach hayyim. כפל kefel
applies to both animals and inanimate objects. ומידת תשלומי ארבעה וחמישה אינה
נוהגת אלא בשור ושה בלבד, umidat tashlumei arba ve-chamisha einah noheget ella
beshor vaseh bilvad, and ד"ה daled hey only applies to a cow
and a sheep. שנאמר, shene'emar, כי יגנוב איש שור או שה, ki
yignov ish shor o seh, if a person steals an ox or
a sheep, וטבחו או מכרו, utvacho o mecharo, and slaughters it or
sells it, וגומר. vegomer. So that's an explicit פסוק pasuk that includes
that special הלכה halacha about that fine and it doesn't apply to
anything else. So אין הגנב אחר הגנב משלם תשלומי כפל, ein haganav
achar haganav meshalem tashlumei kefel, a thief who steals from a thief
does not pay כפל. kefel. ולא הטובח ולא המוכר אחר הגנב, velo
hatove'ach velo hamocher achar haganav, and if a person had already stolen
the animal and then a different person comes and slaughters it or
sells it, that is, two different people did the theft first and
then the slaughtering or selling,
does not pay תשלומי ארבעה וחמישה. tashlumei arba ve-chamisha. They don't pay
ד"ה daled hey in that case because two different people were involved,
and the גנב מן הגנב, ganav min haganav, person stole from a
thief, we're going to see is a special לימוד. limud. רש"י Rashi
says, דכתיב וגונב מבית האיש, de-chtiv ve-gunav mibeit ha-ish, it was stolen
from the person's house, ולא מבית הגנב, velo mibeit haganav, and not
from the thief's house. So stealing from a thief doesn't have the
same level of liability as stealing from the original owner. Interestingly enough,
we see in בבא בתרא Bava Batra and a few other places
cases where actually the original owner tries to steal back the object
from the thief, he felt he wasn't getting due process in the
courts, cases come up as well. So the גמרא Gemara is going
to ask about this word מרובה. meruba. You see there's this long
תוספות Tosafot here, we're going to get to that in just a
second. Okay, so ואילו מידת תשלומי כפל נוהגת בין בגנב בין בטוען
טענת גנב. be-ilu midat tashlumei kefel noheget bein beganav bein betoein ta'anat
ganav. What about the fact that כפל kefel
applies both to גנב, ganav, a thief, and also טוען טענת גנב?
toein ta'anat ganav? We dealt with this about a week ago. טוען
טענת גנב toein ta'anat ganav is a case of a A שומר,
shomer, a שומר shomer is watching an object. In this case, it
must be a שומר חנם. shomer chinam. A שומר חנם shomer chinam
tries to exempt his liability by saying that the object was lost.
Sorry, not was lost, was stolen. שומר חנם shomer chinam is not
liable if the object is stolen. Therefore, he should get off scot-free.
He has to take שבועת השומרים shvuas hashomrim a דאורייתא de'oraysa oath
to exempt himself, like I said before, נשבע ונפטר. nishba veniftar. And
then witnesses come and prove that in fact he had been lying
and he had stolen the object himself. Then such a person is
called טוען טענת גנב, toen ta'anas gannav, that is it was a
שומר shomer who made a claim that the object had been stolen,
is proven wrong, and so he has to obviously he has to
give back the object, but also he has to pay כפל kefel
according to this גמרא. Gemara. That is טוען טענת גנב toen ta'anas
gannav is categorized similarly to גנב. gannav. That is טוען טענת גנב
toen ta'anas gannav claiming that the object was stolen is like being
a thief yourself. Interestingly enough, there're going to be other exceptions to
that we're going to see. ומדת תשלומי ארבעה וחמשה דלאו בהא פליג
אינה נוהגת אלא בגנב בלבד. Umidas tashlumei arba'ah vachamishah delav beha palig
einah noheges ela begannav bilvad. And ארבעה וחמשה arba'ah vachamishah does not
apply in טוען טענת גנב. toen ta'anas gannav. So isn't that one
more way by which כפל kefel is more expansive than ארבעה וחמשה?
arba'ah vachamishah? ולא קתני, Velo kasani, and it wasn't mentioned in the
משנה. Mishnah So the question, implicit question here is shouldn't the משנה
have listed all of the ways in which כפל kefel is more
expansive than ארבעה וחמשה? arba'ah vachamishah? מסייע ליה לרבי חייא בר אבא
דאמר רבי חייא בר אבא אמר רבי יוחנן, Mesayei lei le'Rabbi Chiya
bar Abba de'amar Rabbi Chiya bar Abba amar Rabbi Yochanan, this supports
the opinion of רבי חייא בר אבא Rabbi Chiya bar Abba who
quoted from רבי יוחנן: Rabbi Yochanan: הטוען טענת גנב בפיקדון משלם תשלומי
כפל. Hatoen ta'anas gannav bepikadon meshalem tashlumei kefel. Someone who claims that
the object he was watching was
stolen does pay back כפל. kefel. טבח ומכר משלם תשלומי ארבעה וחמשה.
Tavach umachar meshalem tashlumei arba'ah vachamishah. And if he slaughtered it or
sold it, he does pay ארבעה וחמשה. arba'ah vachamishah. That is don't
distinguish between ארבעה וחמשה arba'ah vachamishah and כפל kefel regarding טוען טענת
גנב. toen ta'anas gannav. איכא דאמרי, Ika de'amrei, there are those who
would say it differently. לימא מסייע ליה לרבי חייא בר אבא דאמר
רבי חייא בר אבא אמר רבי יוחנן הטוען טענת גנב בפיקדון משלם
תשלומי כפל. Leima mesayei lei le'Rabbi Chiya bar Abba de'amar Rabbi Chiya
bar Abba amar Rabbi Yochanan hatoen ta'anas gannav bepikadon meshalem tashlumei kefel.
If you were טוען טענת גנב, toen ta'anas gannav, you pay back
כפל. kefel. טבח ומכר משלם תשלומי ארבעה וחמשה. Tavach umachar meshalem tashlumei
arba'ah vachamishah. And if you slaughtered it or sold it, then you
pay back four and five.
So מי קתני אין בין, mi kasani ein bein, does the משנה
say אין בין, ein bein, these are the only differences? Like we
have the משניות Mishnayos in מסכת מגילה Masechet Megillah that list many
different things and there's אין בין שבת ליום הכיפורים ein bein Shabbos
l'Yom HaKippurim and things like that, all of the limiting the distinction
only to one specific or a few specific details. No, מרובה קתני,
Meruba kasani, it just says מרובה. meruba. כפל Kefel has more applicabilities
than ארבעה וחמשה. arba'ah vachamishah. תנא ושייר, Tana veshayar, so the תנא
Tanna listed a few things and left over a few for the
list. תוספות Tosafos has a big question. The first תוספות, Tosafos, מי
קתני אין בין וכולי. mi kasani ein bein v'chulei. משמע הכא היכא
דתני אין בין לא שייך למימר תנא ושייר. Mashma hacha heicha desani
ein bein lo shayach lemeimar tana veshayar. Therefore, says תוספות, Tosafos, it
must be if the משנה says אין בין, ein bein, then there
are no exceptions. Nothing was left off the list. And when it
says אין בין ein bein there are no differences, it must mean
there are no differences. Comes the רי מאורלינש Ri me'Orleans ממה דתנן
פרק קמא דמגילה אין בין נדרים לנדבות mi'ma desnan perek kama di'Megillah
ein bein nedarim lindavos and he goes through all of these examples
to show actually it's not true. Actually undermining the idea of if
you want to read מרובה meruba to be the equivalent of אין
בין ein bein or somewhat similar. So מרובה meruba first of all,
things are left off the list, and even אין בין ein bein
there are things left off the list. That is
the rabbinic lists are not always pristine. The משנה lists things for
convenience but not necessarily to be exhaustive. So that's actually an important
distinction. Okay, the next part is a very long סוגיא sugya that
we can at least get a little bit of a start on,
but it goes for quite a long time, which is all of
these דרשות drashos about how to apply כפל kefel and ארבעה וחמשה.
arba'ah vachamishah. So let's see. מנא הני מילי? Mena hanei milei? How
do we know about the difference and applicability between כפל kefel and
ארבעה וחמשה? arba'ah vachamishah? דתנו רבנן, Detanu rabanan, על כל דבר פשע.
al kol davar pesha. The פסוק pasuk says about a case of
it was talking about when you bring when you bring
a שבועה shvuah for שומרים. shomrim. כלל על שור על חמור על
שה על שלמה. klal al shor al chamor al seh al salmah.
So then the תורה says about שומרים, shomrim, it lists off several
specific things about an ox, about a donkey, about a sheep, or
about a piece of clothing. פרט על כל אבידה. prat al kol
aveidah. And then so that's פרט, prat, sorry, those are the details.
על כל אבידה, al kol aveidah, for everything that was lost, חזר
וכלל. chazar vechalal. So it says כלל פרט וכלל. klal prat ukhlal.
It was general, then it got specific, and then it was general
again. כלל ופרט וכלל אי אתה דן אלא כעין הפרט. Klal uprat
ukhlal ee atah dan ela ke'ein haprat. So then we limit the
applicability of the כלל klal to the types of things listed in
the פרט, prat, that is the פרט, prat, the sandwich meat between
the bread of the כלל. klal. So the פרט prat which is
in the middle comes to delineate the applicability of the כלל. klal.
So כעין הפרט מה הפרט מפורש דבר המטלטל וגופו ממון, ke'ein haprat
mah haprat meforash davar hametaltel vegufu mamon, just like the פרט prat
are things which are movable, that is not land, and גופו ממון,
gufu mamon, they have intrinsic value, אף כל דבר המיטלטל וגופו ממון
af kol davar hamitaltel vegufu mamon so too. for things which are
movable and they have intrinsic value. יצאו קרקעות, yatzu karkaot, so that
excludes land שאינן מטלטלין she'einan metaltelin because they are not movable. יצאו
עבדים שהוקשו לקרקעות yatzu avadim shehukshu lekarkaot and slaves are exempted because
slaves are connected conceptually to the idea of land, we've seen that
in a number of places. יצאו שטרות yatzu shtaros and exclude documents,
documents presumably deeds of ownership for land, although we'll see perhaps שטרות
shtaros for debts as well, it's a bit of an interesting question.
יצאו שטרות שאף על פי שמטלטלין אין גופן ממון, yatzu shtaros she'af
al pi shemetaltelin ein gufan mamon, even though they are movable, they
do not have intrinsic value. תוספות Tosfos here brings up the question
about שטרות, shtaros, ah it must be גרמי. garmi. If you burn
someone's שטר, shtar, that's only דיני דגרמי dinei degarmi because the שטר
shtar does not have any intrinsic value. So question of course how
does that get into things like stocks and checks and things like
that? Even our money nowadays you might even say is not really
money in the same way, even our money might operate as a
certain kind of a שטר. shtar. And then taking someone's money, ripping
up someone's $100 bill, things like that, gets you into this whole
question of דיני דגרמי. dinei degarmi. So it's a very interesting question.
Certainly tearing up a check is much closer to a kind of
דיני דגרמי, dinei degarmi, a check has no intrinsic value in the
same way. So אין גופן ממון. ein gufan mamon. There was a
long article about checks in Rabbi Bleich's, one of Rabbi Bleich's books
I think. Okay, אין גופן ממון. ein gufan mamon. יצא הקדש. yatzu
hekdesh. So הקדש hekdesh is also excluded from these הלכות. רעהו כתיב,
re'ehu ketiv, it says your friend and we know that רעהו re'ehu
comes to exclude הקדש. hekdesh. אי מה הפרט מפורש דבר שנבלתו מטמא
במגע ובמשא, ei ma haprat meforash davar she'neveylato metamei be'maga u'masa, ah
isn't it true that the פרט, prat, that is the things that
we listed, also comes to include, to limit the applicability in this
case to things which their corpses are מטמא במגע ובמשא, metamei be'maga
u'masa, if you touch them or if you carry them, that is
dead animals, animal carcass. אף על כל דבר שנבלתו מטמא במגע ובמשא,
af al kol davar she'neveylato metamei be'maga u'masa, but only for things
whose corpses are מטמא, metamei, cause impurity to spread either by touching
them or carrying them, אבל עופות לא, aval ofos lo, but not
for birds. Okay, so that's a suggestion that is, and that's going
to be rejected. So birds have a different הלכה halacha of נבלה.
neveylah. נבלת העוף neveylas ha'of is only מטמא בבית הבליעה, metamei be'veis
habliyah, that is only מטמא metamei when you're eating it, but it
doesn't, it doesn't transmit impurity when you touch it or carry it
like a נבלה neveylah from an animal. So there's a lot of
למדות lamdus about נבלת העוף, neveylas ha'of, how is it really like
נבלה, neveylah, but it's a special way of touching it, you only
touch it with your throat, or is it actually a totally different
kind of טומאה tumah and a totally different way that it's transferred.
מי איתמר הכי? mi iytmar hachi? והא שלמה כתיב. veha salma ketiv.
What do you mean?
There's a fourth thing on the list, it's not just animals. There's
a shirt mentioned on the list as well, and shirts don't have
נבלה. neveylah. There's no such thing as a נבלה neveylah shirt. Okay,
okay. אמרי אנן בבעלי חיים קאמרינן. amri anan be'ba'alei chayim kamrina. No,
we were talking about the animals on the list are all mammals,
that is an ox, a donkey, and a sheep, and their נבלה
neveylah is מטמא במגע ובמשא metamei be'maga u'masa unlike birds. That is
to distinguish those three from birds. Okay. So אמרי אנן בבעלי חיים
קאמרינן, amri anan be'ba'alei chayim kamrina, אימא בבעלי חיים דבר שנבלתו מטמא
במגע ובמשא אין דבר שאין נבלתו מטמא במגע ובמשא לא. eima be'ba'alei
chayim davar she'neveylato metamei be'maga u'masa in davar she'ein neveylato metamei be'maga
u'masa lo. So that should lead us to the distinction between animals
whose corpses are מטמא במגע ובמשא, metamei be'maga u'masa, that is mammalian
carcasses as opposed to bird carcasses, and they should be excluded. דהא
כל חד וחד כלל ופרט דאפי נפשיה דרשינן ליה. de'ha kol chad
u'chad klal u'prat de'apei nafshei darshinan lei. Because each one of the
four things on the list you can דרשן darshen your own כלל
ופרט וכלל klal u'prat u'klal based on it. That is we have
the כלל klal first, then we have פרט prat number one, פרט
prat number two, פרט prat number three, and פרט prat number four,
and then we have a כלל klal again. So between the כלל
klal we can always make a new דרשה drasha with each of
the פרטי. pratei. That would be the way it would work. Okay.
And if you could make each one its own דרשה, drasha, then
you can separate the animals separate from the clothing because clothing obviously
the laws of נבלה neveylah don't apply to clothing in that way.
אבל עופות לא. aval ofos lo. And therefore it should exclude birds.
אם כן נכתוב רחמנא חד פרטא. in kein nictov rachmana chad prata.
It should just mention one פרט, prat, that is only mention one
of the animals. הא נכתוב רחמנא, ha nictov rachmana, אי נכתוב רחמנא
שור הוה אמינא קרב לגבי מזבח אין שאין קרב לגבי מזבח לא.
ei nictov rachmana shor hava amina karav legabei mizbe'ach in she'ein karav
legabei mizbe'ach lo. The fact that it would have said שור, shor,
an ox, I would have thought only animals which are brought as
קרבנות. korbanos. אה נכתוב רחמנא חמור, ah nictov rachmana chamor,
because it wouldn't have mentioned donkeys. And if it had only mentioned
donkeys, הוה אמינא קדוש בבכירה אין שאין קדוש בבכירה לא. hava amina
kadosh bivchira in she'ein kadosh bivchira lo. And the donkeys have a
special הלכה halacha about donkeys which only applies to donkeys, which is
the הלכה halacha of פטר חמור, peter chamor, that is the firstborn
donkey from a donkey is the only non-kosher animal that has a
דין din similar to a בכור, bechor, firstborn animal, and the firstborn
donkey has to be redeemed with a sheep, and the sheep has
to be given to the כהן. kohen. So לא אמרי. lo amri.
אם כן נכתוב רחמנא שור וחמור. in kein nictov rachmana shor vechamor.
So it should have said an ox and a donkey, that is
to include all of the non-kosher animals and all of the kosher
animals
because we would not have limited it to animals
Because it mentioned a kosher mammal again. We already had שור, shor,
so the fact that it mentions שה seh comes to include birds.
That is, we're trying to understand in what ways are the laws
of כפל kefel and ד' וה', daled ve-hei, in this case כפל,
kefel, limited. So in this case we're saying well maybe it should
be limited to not apply if you stole someone's chicken. Comes the
word שה seh and the word שה seh comes to include עופות,
ofot, to include birds. Okay, I think that's a good place to
stop. This, as I said, is a long סוגיא, sugya, we're really
stopping in the middle. This is going through all of the details
and how these דרשות drashot play out, but we'll get further treatment
tomorrow. It continues most if not all of tomorrow's דף. daf. All
right.